Inventory of the Armistead-Cocke Papers 1680-1907
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Armistead-Cocke Papers, 1680-1907.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 Ar6
ca. 733 items.
Letters and papers of the Armistead and Cocke families of Henrico and Cumberland Counties, Virginia.
Armistead Family.; Cocke Family.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 296 items, 1958.
Gift: ca. 150 items, 1997.
Gift: 287 items, 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
Maria Carter, daughter of Charles Carter of "Cleve," King George County, Virginia married William Armistead of "Hesse," Gloucester County, Virginia William Cocke, son of Elizabeth Fauntleroy Cocke and Bowler Cocke, married Jane Armistead. Their son, William Armistead Cocke had among other children, Thomas Lewis Preston Cocke who married Mary Booth Curtis.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, 1756-1764, of Maria Carter Armistead; business papers, 1782-1828, of William Cocke of "Bremo," Henrico County, Virginia and of "Oakland," Cumberland County, Virginia; and letters, 1861-1863, of William Fauntleroy Cocke, Thomas Lewis Preston Cocke and Edmund Randolph Cocke concerning their service in the Confederate States Army (including the Battle of First Bull Run). Also included are five volumes of farm and account books, 1851-1863, of Richard P. Jones of "Land's End," Gloucester County, Virginia; copybooks on astronomy, [ca.1770-1780?], scrapbooks, and genealogical material. Includes letter, 1869, of Benjamin Stoddert Ewell concerning the connections between the Randolph and Preston families and the College of William and Mary.
Additions to the collection (1997.34 and 1998.45) include family letters, genealogical notes and poems of members of the Cocke family and to related branches of Throckmorton, Curtis, Sheldon, Jones, Preston, Byrd, Dandridge and Carter families living in Richmond, Virginia and Powhatan County, Virginia. Some letters are written from Richmond in the Reconstruction Era.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged chronologically.
Organization
The inventory has been divided into seven Series. Series 1 is the genealogical and donor material, Series 2 is photographs, Series 3 is material concerning houses and land, Series 4 is correspondence and other papers, Series 5 is the Jones Account Books, Series 6 is Accession 1997.34 and Series 7 is Accession 1998.45.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Armistead family.; Cocke family.; Preston family.; Randolph family.; College of William and Mary--History--19th century.; Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Virginia, 1861.; Astronomy--Study and teaching.; Reconstruction.; Henrico County (Virginia)--History.; Cumberland County (Virginia)--History.; Gloucester County (Virginia)--History.; Powhatan County (Virginia)--History.; Richmond (Virginia)--History.
Persons
Cocke, William, fl. 1798-1855.; Cocke, William Fauntleroy, 1826-1863.; Cocke, Thomas Lewis Preston, 1838-1895.; Cocke, Edmund Randolph, 1841-1922.; Ewell, Benjamin Stoddert, 1810-1894.; Armistead family.; Cocke family.
Component List
  Series 1: Genealogical and Donor Material
- Genealogical and Donor Material, ca. 1958. (Box-folder 1:1-8)
  - Press release, initial list, genealogical charts, ca. 1958. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Press release, 1958. Initial list of the collection. Genealogical charts.
  - The Times-Dispatch, Richmond, 1913., Cl. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Re: Genealogical Column, about Carters and Armisteads.
  - Secondary material concerning collection and Armistead and Carter families, Late 19th century., Incomplete L. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Early Carter and Armistead families, containing copies of letters from this collection.
  - Genealogical material, MO. S. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Genealogical material concerning the Curtis, Sheldon, Carter, and Cocke families by Maria C. Talcott.
  - Descendants of Sir John Randolph, Cl. (Box-folder 1:5)
    From The Times-Dispatch, Richmond
  - Copy of tombstone inscription of Emanuel Jones, Ms. Cop. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Copy of the tombstone of Emanuel Jones, died 1739, made by P[eyton] H. Page.
  - Bible Records, Ms. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Re: Major Robert Throckmorton and John Peyton Dixon, from Bible owned by Mrs. Fann Throckmorton Nicolson.
  - Throckmorton Family of England and Virginia, Oct. 19, 26, and Nov. 2., Cl. (Box-folder 1:8)
    The Sun, Baltimore. Re: The Throckmorton family of England and Virginia by Jane Griffin Keys.
  Series 2: Photographs
- Photographs, n.d., 5 items. PH. (Box-folder 1:9-13)
  - Photograph of painting of Betsy Fauntleroy, n.d., PH (Box-folder 1:9)
    Photograph of painting in Alexandria. She married Bowler Cocke II, and their son was William Cocke who married Jane Armistead.
  - Photograph of painting of Maria Byrd, n.d., Negative and positive photostat. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Photostat positive and negative of painting, owned by Mrs. Maria C. and [Nathan?] Talcott, of Maria Byrd, daughter of William Byrd II and wife of Charles Carter, with son Charles Carter and [Maria Carter Armistead?].
  - Photograph of Thomas Lewis Preston Cocke, n.d., PH. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Thomas Lewis Preston Cocke, son of William Armistead Cocke, Oakland.
  - Photograph of Mrs. Elizabeth Randloph Preston Cocke, n.d., PH. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Mrs. Elizabeth Randolph Preston Cocke, with Sally Lyle Preston Cocke, eldest daughter of Edmund Randolph Cocke.
  - Photograph of Mary Booth Curtis Cocke, n.d., PH. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Mary Booth Curtis Cocke, wife of Thomas L. P. Cocke.
  Series: Materials concerning houses and land
- Materials concerning houses and land, 1680-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 1:14-27)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning Hesse, n.d., Cl. (Box-folder 1:14)
    "Historic Mansion of Mathews County," Hesse.
  - Photograph of Oakland, n.d., PH. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Oakland. Short History on back.
  - Mrs. Cocke of Derwent, n.d., Cl. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Mrs. Cocke, Mistress of Oakland and Hostess of the Lees at Derwent, by Alice M. Tyler from The Times-Dispatch, Richmond.
  - Photograph of "Derwent", n.d., Ph. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Article on Derwent, June 17, 1947., Cl. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Derwent Must Be Saved from The News Leader, Richmond, Virginia.
  - Lee's Hideaway Still Stands n.d., Cl. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Lee's Hideaway Still Stands. Reprinted from The Washington and Lee University Alumni Magazine by Dr. Leslie Lyle Campbell.
  - Southerner Heard First and Last Shots of War n.d. (Box-folder 1:20)
    Southerner Heard First and Final Shots of War Between States, was friend of Lee, by Charles F. Preston.
  - Plat of land on Piantatank River, [ca. 1680]., Ms. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Part of plat. Showing land on the Piantantan River of Lady Skipwith, George Curtis, Collonell [sic] Kemps, Augustin Horthus and William Marloe.
  - Deed of land from Thomas Curtis, December 30, 1689., DS. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Sale of land in Kingston Parish, inherited from George Curtis, who bought the land from Edward Wyatt.
  - Deed of land from Thomas Curtis, December 30, 1689., DS. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Thomas Curtis, Gloucester County to Charles Curtis, Middlesex County Re: Deed of same date was to fulfill Thomas' bond to Charles.
  - Testimony of Nicholas Cobb, February 19, 1695., DS Cop. (Box-folder 1:24)
    P. Beverly, Clerk of County Court. Re: Testimony of Nicholas Cobb, defendant; by his attorney, Thomas Gregson, in dispute over land purchased from George Curtis, now deceased.
  - Will of Charles Curtis, ca. 1700., D. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:25)
    Charles Curtis, Kingston Parish, Gloucester CountyHis will Gives all land to son Augustine, to daughters Sarrah [sic] Henry and Sous Anna [sic] Iveson, Negroes and linens
  - Plat of land of Charles Curtis, ca. 1700., Ms. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Plat of land. Charles Curtis on Piantatank River to Jno. West, Chisanassirk River, Accomack County Plat showing land surveyed by Jno. Smith. Shows location of the house.
  - Floor Plan of House, [ca. 1760]., Ms. Note watermark. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Nicholas Foster. Re: Floor plan of a house.
  Series 4: Papers
- Letters, accounts and papers of the Armistead-Cocke family, 1756-1844. (Box 1-4)
  - Maria Carter, daughter of Landon Carter, Sabine Hall to Maria Carter, Cleve, daughter of Charles Carter, March 25, 1756., ALS in fragments. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Re: How to stay busy during the day. Published in 15 V 432.
  - Maria Byrd, nee Taylor, Westover, to Maria Carter, her granddaughter, Cleve, February [1763]., AL. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Requests that the family visit her at Westover.
  - Marie Carter of Cleve Copy Book, 1763., Ms. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Bound in letter, April 14, 1792, from Christopher Pryor to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse.
  - Maria Byrd, Westover, to Molly Maria Carter, Cleve, December 24, 1763., ALS. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Cousin Maria Carter, daughter of Landon Beverley, gave birth to a son in October. Uncle William III and Aunt Mary Willing Byrd are going to tour through New York and Philadelphia. Health. Published in 10 V 178.
  - Charles Carter, Cleve, Virginia to Molly Maria Carter his daughter, January 25, 1764., ALS. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Pocket money for her visiting. Cautions against flattery. Publixhed in 10 V 178.
  - Maria Carter, daughter of Landon, Sabine Hall, Beverly Blandfield to Molly Maria Carter, daughter of Charles, of Cleve, April 20, 1764., ALS. in fragments. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Coming marriages of Lucy Burwell to Edmund Berkeley, Rebecca Burwell to Jaquelin Amble and Jenny Burwell to Mann Page of Rosewell, and Miss Hannah Fairfax to Warner Washington. Published in 10 V 177-178 and 15 V 433-434.
  - Maria Byrd nee Taylor, Westover to Maria Carter, her granddaughter, Cleve, [1765]., AL torn. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Concerns Mr. William Armistead. Published in 15 V 435.
  - Landon Carter, Sabine Hall to Molly Maria Carter, daughter of Charles of Cleve, February 19, 1765., ALS in fragments. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Family news.
  - William Byrd II, Westover to his niece Molly Maria Carter, November 25, 1765., ALS. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Re: Her marriage to Mr. William Armistead. Published in 10 V 179-180 and 15 V 435.
  - Warner Lewis to William Armistead, his cousin, Hesse, May 16, 1768., ALS. in fragments. (Box-folder 1:37)
    Vote getting. Lewis' coming marriage. Launching of ship by the father of Lewis.
  - Augustine Curtis to R. Carter Nicolson Ca. 1770., L. Dr. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Suit against Clark Courtney and his mother Anne Mabry concerning land "at Eatons warehouse on Rappahannock River."
  - Ann Brown, New York to Maria Carter Armistead, April 3, 1772. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Virginians' reaction to Lord Dunmore as Governor Tryon is well received at New York, as is Col. Fanning. Family news. Part published in 10 V 180.
  - Account book and accounts of Augustine Curtis, May 1772- March 1774., MS. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Accounts with William Jackson, James Clark, Major Thomas Boswell, John Robinson, Richard Hodges, Robert Matthewes, William Bentley Estate, Francis Elliot and John Hibble.
  - Receipt of W.W. Russel, Richmond to William Cocke, August 14, 1773. (Box-folder 1:41)
  - Bond of Indemnity, March 3, 1774. (Box-folder 1:42)
    John New, John Fox and Danall New, Senior to William Armistead, Sheriff, Gloucester County Re: Bond of Indemnity.
  - Inventory of the estate of Augustine Curtis, deceased, January 15, 1775., MS. (Box-folder 1:43)
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas, to Maria Armistead, Hesse, June 5, 1775., ALS in fragments. (Box-folder 1:44)
    Visit of Mr. William and Mrs. Armistead to their church. Route over Pudding Creek Bridge.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas, the Glebe to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse, January 3, 1776., ALS. (Box-folder 1:44)
    News about fighting in Norfolk and man of war near York. Sent cotton and worsted.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse, February 8, 1776., ALS. (Box-folder 1:45)
    The Armisteads' moving North River to avoid the enemy. The Armisteads have kept prisoners.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas to Maria Armistead, June 3, 1776., ALS. (Box-folder 1:47)
    The evils and hardships brought upon the people by persons without authority.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas to Maria Armistead June 13., ALS. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Submission to the catastrophies brought by man and God. News of the Russian General, and General Howe building on the Delaware.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse, March 5, 1778., ALS. (Box-folder 1:50)
    Birth of Mrs. Armistead's child. Capt. Deane carried Major Skith in his ship. Resignation to the will of Providence.
  - E. Feilde Mrs. Thomas, New York, to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse, August 17, 1779., ALS. (Box-folder 1:51)
    Mr. Smith came to Elizabeth Town, N.J. but was denied a permit for New York. Lack of Negroes.
  - Aug. Bagner to Mrs. Maria Armistead, 1780-1792?., 4 items. MS. (Box-folder 1:52)
    Accounts.
  - Clement Richard to Mrs. Maria Armistead, 1780-92?., MS. S. (Box-folder 1:54)
  - To William Fleming, 1780-1800., MS. (Box-folder 1:55)
    Memorandum of money received.
  - William Cocke, 1770-1780., MS. V. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Copy book on Astronomy.
  - William Cocke, Henrico County to John Taylor Griffin, Goochland County [Virginia] Bond, 1782-1783., Fragments D. (Box-folder 2:3)
    On reverse, John T. Griffin assigns the bond to Major William Lewis.
  - To William Cocke, Bremo, Henrico County, Virginia, 1782-1789., C. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Pennock, Nicolson and Skipwith to William Cocke, 1786., MS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Account for the year.
  - Moore Fauntleroy, Nayors Hole to William Cocke, Bremo, his cousin, February 27, 1786., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Money payment in Half Joes. Land papers brought from Augusta.
  - John R. Grymes, London to Thomas Taylor Byrd, husband of Mary A. Armistead, March 1786., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:6)
    "Invoice of Sundry Goods Shipped on board the Planter Capt. William Arthurs for Virginia..." Furniture, linens, carpets, dishes and silverware.
  - Landon Carter, Cleve to Sister Maria Armistead?, June 20, 1787., ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Corn and wheat deliveries, requested by Mr. Lynham. Her son Charles Carter Armistead is placed with Mr. Waugh in Port Royal.
  - Crowley, Millington and County to Messrs. Donald and Burton, July 10, 1787., MS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Account for nails and German steel.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to Genl. Alexander Spotswood, Virginia, November 10, 1787., MS. (Box-folder 2:9)
    "Invoice of Sundries shipped on board the Ann& Mary, Capt. John Wheeler..." Horses, tools, medical implements, riding equipment and spices.
  - "Memorandum of Goods to be shipped to William Cocke," from Rowles Grymes and Co, 1788-90., MS. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Lucy Armistead to Mrs. Maria Armistead, Hesse, her mother, February 10, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:12)
    Lucy's visit to home of Col. William Byrd III?. Published in 10 V 183.
  - Charles Carter, Shirley to Maria Armistead, Hesse, March 17, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Offers to send Negro girls to help her daughter.
  - Benjamin Hammatt, London to Rowles Grymes and County, April 3, 1788., D. S. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Protests the manner of payment of bill of exchange. Includes copy of request for bill of exchange from William Cocke to Rowles Grymes and County, London, November 30, 1787.
  - William Cocke, Bremo to Rowles Grymes and County, London, April 4, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Sends tobacco to be sold to cover cost of requested items. Draws a bill of exchange upon them.
  - M.? Byrd, Westover to William Cocke, Bremo, April 10, 1788. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Agreement about Negroes written by Mr. Page.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, Virginia May 4, 1788., L. S. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Return of Cocke's bill of exchange resulted from his not reporting it.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, Virginia May 4, 1788., L. S.[copy]. (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Landon Carter, Cleve to Mrs. [Anne] Willis [his sister], Willis Hall, May 14, 1788., ALS (Box-folder 2:19)
    Children's education in spelling, Greek, and reading. The new Constitution will lead to a navy.
  - Maria Armistead, Fredericksburg to [son-in-law] William Cocke, Bremo, May 31, 1788?., ALS. (Box-folder 2:20)
    Her brother Charles [Carter] will send for her daughters. Plans to return to Hesse soon.
  - Mich[ae]l Tose to William Cocke, June 25, 1788., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:21)
    Shipment of tobacco sent by the ship Williamson under John Miers to Rowles Grymes and County
  - Philip L. Grymes, Brandon to William Cocke, Bremo, June 26, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:22)
    Shipment of tobacco and other goods.
  - Mary [Willing] Byrd to Mrs. [Maria] Armistead, Hesse, Sep[tember] 1, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Damages from a hurricane. A [legal] "execution". Aunt and Uncle [Lewis] Willis.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, Virginia, Septem[ber] 5, 1788., ALS. (Box-folder 2:24)
    Arrival of tobacco and confusion of orders.
  - To William Cocke, 1789., MS. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Accounts against Cocke. On Reverse, note from Mr. Weaver and W.A. Fry.
  - Fredericksburg Academy, to Mrs. [Ann Champe] Willis [sister to Mrs. Maria Carter Armistead], January 11, 1789., MS. (Box-folder 2:26)
    Receipt for tuition of Master [Charles Carter] Armistead.
  - Thomas Main, London to William Cocke, Bremo, February 17, 1789., MS. (Box-folder 2:27)
    "Invoice of Goods..." shipped care of P. Parker at Norfolk.
  - Maria Armistead, Willis Hill to Miss Jane Armistead, The Cottage, April 9, [17]89., ALS. (Box-folder 2:28)
    Travelling and illness. Mr. Page and Mr. Byrd may help her move.
  - Anonymous to Lewis Willis, Fredericksburg, May 10, 1789. (Box-folder 2:29)
    Sends by Willis, a tobacco note for Mrs. Maria Armistead's travels.
  - Thomas Ryan to Mrs. Anne Willis daughter of Charles Carter, Cleve, May 15, 1789., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:30)
    Receipt for tuition of Master Charles Carter Armistead.
  - Thomas Satchell, Richmond to William Cocke, June 2, 1789., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:31)
    Receipts for money for Benjamin Harrison Jr.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, near Richmond, July 17, 1789., ALS. (Box-folder 2:32)
    Receipt of Cocke's draft through Alexander Donald.
  - William Cocke, Bremo to Thomas Main, London, July 17, 1789., ALS. (Box-folder 2:33)
    Shipment of tobacco on the Brandon. Requests information on the most popular kinds of tobacco.
  - Receipt for payment for Broad Shoes, August 31, 1789. (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Maria Armistead, Hesse to Rowles Grymes and County, London, 1790., MS. S. Dr. (Box-folder 2:35)
    Items to be sent to the care of P.L. Grymes. Notes of exchange.
  - William Cocke to Mickleberry Mountigue, Ca. 1790., MS. (Box-folder 2:36)
    Account of work done around his house. Lists cost of items used.
  - James Lynham to Miss Armistead, 1790's., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:37)
    Receipt for payment on coffee.
  - Mat to William Andrewdale, 1790s., MS. (Box-folder 2:38)
    Dispute. Copy sent to Mrs. Maria Armistead.
  - Fairfax Washington, Beech Park, Logan County, Kentucky to William Cocke, Cartersville, February 21, 1790-1820?., ALS. (Box-folder 2:39)
    Wife Sally Sarah desires news of her sister Jane Armistead Cole. One of Washington's sisters married Mr. Milton. Growth of the area. Advantages of this farm.
  - Thomas Main, London to William Cocke, February 18, 1790., ALS. Cop. (Box-folder 2:40)
    Sale of Cocke's tobacco which was of poor quality and "injured by the spot."
  - Donald and Burton, London to William Cocke, March 15, 1790., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:41)
    Account of sale of tobacco.
  - Thomas Main, London to William Cocke, March 27, 1790., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:42)
  - Thomas Main, London to William Cocke, March 27, 1790., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:43)
  - John Thompson, Richmond to William Cocke, April 22, 1790., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:44)
    Account due John and Thomas Gilliat for sugar, salt and iron.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, James River, May 20, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:45)
    Death of partner James Rowles. Sale of tobacco.
  - Charles Cocke, Mr. Prospectus to brother William Cocke, Cumberland, May 26, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:46)
    Payment of a debt to prevent having to sell Negroes. His wife Betsy. Miss Nancy Armistead "is almost devoured by Sweet Hearts."
  - Bowler Cocke, Richmond to brother William Cocke, Cumberland, May 27, 1790., May 27, 1790. (Box-folder 2:47)
    Supplies of tea, earthenware, cyder [sic] and herring from Mr. Gilliat. Mother Mrs. Elizabeth Hill Carter Cocke will visit soon.
  - Ann Willis to sister Maria Armistead, May 29, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:48)
    Judy Armistead's ill health; suggests cures. Charles Carter Armistead is over the measles; Mr. Thomas Ryan praises him.
  - James and Thomas Deane, Cumberland to William Cocke, Cumberland, June 10, 1790. (Box-folder 2:49)
    Sends all requested items except loaf sugar.
  - Bowler Cocke, Bremo to brother, William Cocke, Cumberland, July 10, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:50)
    Wheat harvest. Possibility of a Spanish war; Spanish ships have been seen in New York and Virginia. Mentions brother Charles Cocke and his son Henry.
  - Alexander Donald, Richmond to William Cocke, June 17, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:51)
    Confusion in the settlement of Cocke's account with Donald and Barton of London.
  - Bowler Cocke, Richmond to brother William Cocke, Cumberland, July 11, 1790., ALS (Box-folder 2:52)
    At Manchester, with Mr. Pankey, inquired after hogsheads of mother Elizabeth Hill Carter Cocke. Tobacco; one had been sent to William Mitchell.
  - William Cocke to Thomas Main, August 8, 1790., L. Dr. (Box-folder 2:53)
    Poor tobacco sales of the previous crop will prevent his getting out of debt. Present crop does well. People have started growing wheat.
  - J.D. Napier to Fluvanna Country Court, September 28, 1790., D.S. (Box-folder 2:54)
    John Hall brought a runaway Negro to Napier. The boy said he belonged to William Cocke of Cumberland.
  - Rowles Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, James River, September 30, 1790., L.S. Cop. Encl. (Box-folder 2:55)
    Sends account of tobacco shipped in the Williamson.
  - Moore Fauntleroy, Naylor Hole to William Cocke, Cumberland, November 17, 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 2:56)
    His sister Elizabeth Adams wishes Cocke to sell her corn. Consulted Major Thomas Massie and William Fry.
  - J. Montgomery to Sheriff of Amherst Co, 1791., MS. S. (Box-folder 2:57)
    Monies due from estate of Thomas Adams.
  - William Cresey to Elizabeth Adams mother to William Cocke, 1791., MS. (Box-folder 2:58)
    Account for carrying hogsheads to market.
  - William Cocke to Estate of Thomas Adams, 1791., MS. (Box-folder 2:58)
    List of monies due Cocke.
  - Notes and account daling with tuition, by Mr. Woodville, of Charles Carter Armistead, March 1791/2. (Box-folder 2:59)
  - Moses Hughes, John N. Reid to Amherst County Court, January 26, 1791., MS. Cop. (Box-folder 2:60)
    "Appraisement and Inventory of stock and plantation tools and utensils on Mrs. Elizabeth Adames' plantation in Amherst County."
  - Robert Coventry, Richmond to William Cocke, Cumberland, February 1, 1791., ALS. (Box-folder 2:61)
    Acting for James Brown, sends coffee, and iron by Mr. Fenwick. Prices given.
  - T.R. Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, James River, February 10, 1791., ALS. Encl. (Box-folder 2:62)
    Sends account and asks it be paid up, to enable the settlement of the estate of James Grymes.
  - T.R. Grymes and County, London to William Cocke, James River, February 10, 1791., ALS. Encl. Cop. (Box-folder 2:64)